Let's see what this looks like in the most general case,
我们来看适用性最广的情况
where your matrix has entries a, b, c,
此时矩阵有 a、b、c、d 四个项
d. And remember, this matrix is just a way of
记住 这个矩阵只是把
packaging the information needed to describe a linear transformation.
描述线性变换所需的信息打包起来了
Always remember to interpret that first column, a, c,
请牢记 第一列的值 a 和 c
as the place where the first basis vector lands and that second column,
是第一个基向量移动后的坐标
b,d, as the place where the second basis vector lands.
第二列的值 b 和 d 是第二个基向量移动后的坐标
When we apply this transformation to some vector x,
对某个向量 [x , y] 进行这个变换
y, what do you get?
结果是什么呢？
Well, it will be x times a,
其实就是 x 乘 [a , c]
c, plus, y times b,
加 y 乘 [b , d]
d. Putting this together,
求和
you get a vector ax + by, cx + dy.
你就得到了向量 [ax + by , cx + dy]
You could even define this as
你甚至可以将这个过程定义为
matrix vector multiplication when you put
矩阵向量相乘
the matrix on the left of the vector like it's a function.
把矩阵放在向量的左侧 就跟函数一样
Then you could make high schoolers memorize this without
然后让高中生直接背诵这条公式
showing them the crucial part that makes it feel intuitive.
省略掉中间这个对理解至关重要的部分
But isn't it more fun to think about
但把这些列
these columns as the transformed versions of your basis vectors,
看作变换后的基向量
and to think about the results as the appropriate linear combination of those vectors?
把结果看作这些向量进行适当线性组合后的产物 难道不是更有趣吗？
Let's practice describing a few linear transformations with matrices.
我们再来看其它用矩阵描述线性变换的例子
For example, if we rotate all of space 90 degrees counter-clockwise,
如果把整个空间逆时针旋转九十度
then i_hat lands on the coordinates (0,
î 就会落在坐标 [0 , 1] 上
1,) and j_hat lands on the coordinates (-1, 0).
ĵ 则落在坐标 [-1 , 0] 上
So the matrix we end up with has columns (0, 1) (-1,
于是我们得到的矩阵就有两列 分别是 0 和 1 以及 -1 和 0
0) to figure out what happens to any vector after a 90 degree rotation.
要求经过九十度旋转后的任意向量
You could just multiply its coordinates by this matrix.
只需用该向量的坐标乘以这个矩阵
Here's a fun transformation with a special name called a shear.
现在我们来讲一个有趣的变换 叫做剪切变换
In it, i_hat remains fixed.
其中 î 不变
So, the first column of The Matrix is 1,
所以矩阵第一列还是 1 和 0
0 but j_hat moves over to the coordinates (1,
但 ĵ 移动到了坐标 [1 , 1] 处
1) which become the second column of The Matrix.
所以矩阵第二列发生了变化
And at the risk of being redundant here,
这里我要啰嗦一句
figuring out how a shear transforms a given vector
要求经过剪切变换的某个向量
comes down to multiplying this matrix by that vector.
只需让该向量和矩阵相乘
Let's say we want to go the other way around.
现在反过来看
Starting with a matrix,
先看矩阵
say with columns 1,
有两列 1 和 2
2 and 3, 1,
3 和 1
and we want to deduce what its transformation looks like.
我们要根据这个矩阵来推导变换公式
Pause and take a moment to see if you can imagine it.
你可以暂停一下 看看能不能想象出变换的情景
One way to do this is to first move i_hat to 1,
推导的办法之一是 先把 î 移动到 [1 , 2] 处
2, then move j_hat to 3, 1.
然后把 ĵ 移动到 [3 , 1] 处
Always moving the rest of space in such a way that
记住要保持空间
keeps grid lines parallel and evenly spaced.
网格线平行且等距分布
If the vectors that i_hat and j_hat land on are linearly dependent,
如果变换后的向量 î 和 ĵ 线性相关
which if you recall from last video means that one is a scaled version of the other,
如果你还记得上个视频的话 你就知道这意味着其中一个向量是另一个向量的缩放版本
it means that the linear transformation squishes all of
也就是说 这个线性变换会把整个二维空间
2D space onto the line where those two vectors sit,
压缩成这两个向量所在的那条直线
also known as the one dimensional span of those two linearly dependent vectors.
也即这两个线性相关向量的一维张成空间
To sum up, linear transformations are a way to move around
总地来说 线性变换就是一种空间变换方法
space such that grid lines remain parallel and evenly spaced,
变换时网格线会保持平行且等距分布
and such that the origin remains fixed.
原点也会保持不变
Delightfully, these transformations can be described using only a handful of numbers,
值得高兴的是 这些变换可以用少数几个数字来描述
the coordinates of where each basis vector lands.
也即每个基向量移动后所处的坐标
Matrices give us a language to describe these transformations where the columns represent
矩阵其实是线性变换的一种描述方式
those coordinates and matrix vector multiplication is
矩阵的列就是向量的坐标 矩阵与向量相乘
just a way to compute what that transformation does to a given vector.
其实是计算给定向量如何进行变换的一种方法
The important takeaway here is that every time you see
还有很重要的一点是
a matrix you can interpret it as a certain transformation of space.
看到一个矩阵 你就可以将其看作某种空间变换
Once you really digest this idea,
一旦你彻底理解了这个思路
you're in a great position to understand linear algebra deeply.
你就能深刻地理解线性代数了